we're on uh dinning Arc okay it's again
yeah good okay
uh and by the way I'll stop 15 minutes
before
nine o'clock World Central Dewey time
and uh take questions and answers okay
about any topic I don't care
so here we go dinning
he says this practice of
riding on the breath okay Cowboy Tomlin
on your Prana
she okay key
uh is is actually
related linked to a secret practice okay
knock knock means mantra
in tibetan and Mantra in tibetan means
Tantra
and tandriana same thing okay so he says
there is a high
Diamond way practice that you can do
related to your uh pranayamas and that
connects to YSI so it's kind of like YSI
connects to ACI connects to diamond ring
and um he says
it's related to a practice called
Georgette okay
means diamond
Mantra reciting okay uh
and it's a very high
Diamond wave practice there are 18
courses in Diamond way Tundra that were
developed at Diamond Mountain
it took 14 years
of very hard work by a certain Grandpa
and seven years in New York to prepare
the people 18 courses
about 30 000 pages of translation
and then uh seven years to teach uh
Diamond way here at diamond mountain and
that's about third the whole thing Ellie
I don't know 30 000 pages I don't know
something like that
yeah uh yeah I'm still working on it but
uh
it was a lot of
it's a lot of work I believe
uh and I I was at uh there's only two
tantric colleges in Tibet it's
my teacher was the
Vice habit of give me
so uh he you know we we're familiar with
what they teach
and uh I was there when they opened uh
their debate ground I debated at you may
10 to college
uh in the first weeks that they opened
uh in their
and it was cool okay uh so
the diamond mountain course
in the diamond way is better than the
chorus I'd either tend to call it and I
can say it without hesitation
okay because I've been there and I've
spent time there
and uh the diamond mountain course 18
courses
is is
better organized than any
Diamond way course in history
uh and it's more thorough so anyway
[Music]
um
this practice of diamond recitation is
part of those 18 courses anybody
remember which course I don't know
no okay anyway it's in there okay and if
you get a chance to
uh
take the 18 Advanced courses the diamond
request you should do it okay
okay uh right now uh Peter John Connie
Ellie
are focusing on teaching those Diamond
way courses
and Tim I think and you're very uh
welcome to talk to them
and start to learn it okay if you want
to learn
the secret breathing tongue land
practice
of diamond recitation
you need to learn it properly I I will
not teach it in public okay you need to
learn it from
in the old way
Galaxy sorry
my teacher loved this
Investment Company advertising on TV in
1975.
and there's an old Banker who says uh
we make money the old way
we earning
and he said I love that guy you know and
so you're gonna earn it okay
so talk to one of those guys
and then he quotes he says I can't tell
you about that in a public teaching but
I can refer you okay dude
Jay
Den Jay Jay Lumber okay
Jay Lumber
so kedu
means it's an abbreviation of kitchen
Troopa okay kashin drupa means uh
what do you call it
uh
wise and
practiced or something like that
knowledgeable and practiced and it's a
beautiful word it means a person
who learns the scriptures correctly
and then does retreat and and goes and
doesn't Okay so K means lots of
classroom hours Drew means lots of
retreat hours
and if you call somebody kidu
it's a big compliment we just finished
yesterday
uh mostly uh so gang's new book which is
by kedu dembadage it's a different kid
room
so that's the meaning of kid room okay
there's a famous kid Group which is the
student
Johnson one of the two principal
students of Johnson copper
there's three big names there there's J
and the first dalama
but the first dilemma was just a kid at
the time
so we don't count him much in the
pictures
but he's there okay
okay he taught
or he ordained uh a great teacher from
Center J
uh named Senator Judson
and he taught me
so that's the lineage there's there's a
tight lineage
so
some Compass student
said about
his teacher okay and here's a picture
Daniel
yeah uh when you see this picture
and Grandpa guessing Michael asks you
what's this picture
you're gonna say this is my teacher
breathing
okay this is my teacher breathing and
the diamond mountain lineage
and by the way how it differs from the
lineage
that we came from llama surface lineage
for example
is that we are returning to the days
when Buddhist teachers were either
ordained or not ordained okay
change okay okay originally
a Buddhism was taught by people who were
not ordained in Tibet it was taught by
people who are not ordained
in India also then for a while kind of
the months and nuns took over and
there's a heavy beautiful tradition of
normal people normal
working people
teaching Buddhism to normal working
people which seems to work pretty well
okay so because they understand the
challenges
of normal working people
so I
this guy is a high llama okay
and uh he probably learned his stuff at
Diamond Mountain
tradition there's ancient tradition of
of lay people teaching laypeople and
even teaching monks and nuns
okay so that's very much our tradition
okay okay doesn't matter
what's your background doesn't matter
what country you're from we were the
first
people in the world ACI to teach women
the guessing course okay
and we were heavily criticized
and really badly criticized and then
suddenly they just ordained they just
announced the first woman gache in the
traditional
uh
Monastery we're like yeah well we've did
that before
so anyway
I think it's a great thing okay you're
very welcome to become a teacher I think
you'll make great teachers if you don't
become a teacher you're lazy
okay you should teach okay you should
teach we are like
a major city of 10 million people with
one doctor or two doctors
it's bad situation is bad okay many
people are suffering
because there's not enough doctors Okay
so
if you listen to these teachings
and you don't pass them on Euro what's
that bad word that guess what I would
never say in front of his wife
you're a loser okay
all right
here's kid's description of his teacher
okay
and then you gotta guess why it's here
now
okay just done just to learn okay gumbo
means
my my llama my protector okay who's that
Shout
a single breath from your lips
okay a single breath from your lips
Young
Tada dollar countless living beings men
you know manla
medicine Buddha okay this man means uh
is medicine is sweet medicine for what
all living beings
okay when you oh Jackson copper when you
you are helping countless living beings
okay a single exhalation
a short
single exhalation from your lips is the
service of all living beings you know
this is Caleb Jade talking about his
teacher
and and then says
that's the Goomba
that's what we're talking about
we're talking about
tonglan
being connected to pranayam
okay if you don't know the pranayama
part take YSI course in September right
and they're going through a deep deep
book
about breeding practice and retreat
okay uh and it'll take us two years to
finish I think
about a quarter of the way through
something like that
okay but
it's a secret practice and that's why
kwj said about his own teacher
you just
and countless people are are helped
and if you want to learn that
come to Hawaii
okay
that's the idea of those lines
we're talking about this Secret
practice on the breath
connected with donor okay cool
cool all right I went and got you the
quotation but that's okay
by the way I I use the database of John
Brady's team the Asian Legacy Library
I use it probably a hundred times a day
and and my teaching strongly depends on
it uh when I was in the monastery
finishing the gesh exam
we have uh Intercollegiate geshi exams
we have to debate against other
monasteries
and I showed my team
how to use the database and they're like
now we got them you know and
uh it was so cool you know we wiped out
everybody
uh because every night we were like
you know and finding amazing stuff on
John Brady's done a bit so I'd like to
thank John and his team
[Applause]
and I'd like to thank all the people
supporting John Brody's team and I know
the Gold Club for example is really
important
I'm really grateful
grateful thank you
[Applause]
that that was an interesting fundraising
thing because they they basically asked
people to give five dollars a month
and they've raised a million and a half
dollars and
for John Brady's project so I'd like to
thank them again
I think that's kind of a cool
fundraising thing if everyone gives a
little bit
it's very helpful okay
next line you guys
and don't forget we'll have questions
answer in 15 minutes
um
uh there's lots of deep teachings here
manok means deep teachings
mermaids but
I cannot teach Tantra in a long room
class or I'm not
okay he says go talk to
go talk to these Diamond Way teachers
okay even in the long rim
he says look I'm just giving you a
a little taste
and then you have to learn it properly
from a proper teacher okay
and the teachers at Diamond Mountain are
the most highly trained tantric teachers
in the world
period okay there's a three-year retreat
at you made tentacons they you go stay
in a house in the middle of the
monastery
which is like
what
and they're like that's how we do it I'm
like
yeah but anyway okay
uh and by the way it's a great
institution it's the greatest it's been
there for 600 years
but I think the way it's being done at
diamond mountain is uh is very very
special and and I think very powerful
all right
here comes a whole new section all right
we've actually officially finished
strongman
how what was the last thing he said
I'm not teaching you the real one
go learn it properly
okay then he says let's move on
okay
kind of cruel Germany
[Music]
uh and I put the header there it's
called Turning
uh problems into the path okay it's a
special
Buddhist practice come in
this girl
means transformation and it's the verb
for turning yourself into a cloud turn
yourself into the sun
it means to transform something to
completely okay
and we're about to start a whole section
about the unique Buddhist skill
of consciously looking for difficult
situations
and turning them into wild successes
and it's a wonderful wonderful practice
okay you you purposely
seek out
difficult situations
and then you flip them into this
incredible
success okay and I think
even if you just want to be a business
person or something I think this next
section
is really really wonderful and it
transformed my life you know I
I this okay just listen okay
you learn
to identify problems
and then go eat them
live off them
like candy
okay uh
didn't what is your life
you got the good parts and the bad parts
right if you learn to eat the bad parts
and turn them into the good parts well
what's your life
it's good part all day okay so normally
human life has
good parts and bad parts
and most human beings
try to
hang out in the good parts
and avoid the bad parts including
irritating people and nice people so
it's Human Nature
to try to hang out with the nice people
and to try to avoid the irritating
people if you
learn this part of the alarm Rim you
will reverse your behavior
you will look for [__]
okay and guess what you'll find them
okay all right you are looking for
irritating people and you are looking
for difficult situations tense
situations arguments
dangerous situations
okay and and you're sucking them up
wow that's so nice and you flip them you
learn to flip them if you have good
stuff going on 50 of the time and if you
have bad stuff going on
50 of the time if half the People You
Meet are really nice
and half the People You Meet are really
dumb
and then you focus on the dumb ones and
you focus on the difficult situations
and you have this magical
alarm Rim technique to flip them
then what's your life
your your whole day is fun
and and I I do I do it and I have to say
it it's it works
and it's fun okay 24 hours a day fun
okay every single stupid person you ever
meet is like
another opportunity to have a good day
you know and if you learn this section
uh it's worth all the all the trouble
you took to come to this Retreat okay
then you're looking for difficult
situations
and you're looking for difficult people
if two directors and two organizations
tell you by tomorrow morning Isla can
you come up with a fundraising thing to
cover this by
then you're like yeah
we'll do that
and uh
and you turn it into something really
fun and it helps thousands of people and
uh
okay all right so this part is really
uh beautiful and if you can learn it
there's no such thing as a bad day okay
and just imagine having a good day every
day okay and every time a problem comes
up
you eat it like you're really hungry
like
how does our granddaughter Express
happiness
at this point she's six months exactly
right
and we went to visit her yesterday and
she goes
I said what's going on they said that's
how she expresses happiness
all right okay she's really happy
hopefully later she'll learn to smile
[Laughter]
but imagine all around in your life
turned into something happy
you know imagine
okay so really we gotta learn this
section okay really work hard on this
section okay
because the result of working hard on
this section
is you're having fun all day every day
no matter what happens I was at the
doctor
uh I have my kidneys not not doing great
and and she told me you're like
and I said yeah okay
and she says
she looks at me and she says
she doesn't know what I do and she says
do you meditate
I'm like
a little bit
and just yeah something's weird
you know
so anyway uh
isn't there
that's that's the thing okay
uh what is the next picture you guys
did I not give you a 43.25 I think I
forgot okay let's cancel it
um
we talked about consumer
for two dollars
because we just gave we all our money uh
what's up in regard to react reactions
with other people into interactions
sorry
yeah between what
yeah good that's all that's all so in
any situation
with other people you have a choice of
taking care of yourself first
or taking care of others first and in a
traditional Buddhist teaching
and I'm actually thinking of llama simpa
they would talk for hours that you
should sacrifice your
what you want and and take care of what
other people want
and that's I I think there's a deeper
teaching here
uh
that a real Buddhist
Yogi
and what makes you a yogi
is you're faced with a situation
of taking care of what somebody else
wants or
taking care of what you want and you
you cover both
to a to higher than the expectations of
either party
okay the combination of both
gets both parties more than more than
they expected okay got it
the donor gives a lot of money and then
suddenly there's these two-year grants
and both both parties get success both
parties get more than they expected okay
it's a attitude
towards solving problems don't settle
for
taking care of yourself
or taking care of somebody else
don't settle for that settle from both
at a higher degree than either one
individually got it
find clever Solutions
that give each party more than they
expected and by the way that's the key
to a business negotiation we're teaching
business negotiation at the MBA program
I negotiated for 19 years many times
every day that was my job
and uh the ultimate negotiation is both
parties get more than they wanted when
they came to the negotiation
and that's the way it should be okay and
that's tongue man all right that's a
kind of government
okay dear
they shouldn't dependency
by the way uh
now here's the Deep question for today
[Music]
um
why did a teacher who was teaching thong
land suddenly flipped to
turning problems into opportunities
he doesn't give any introduction
he says don't forget this time to
practice on your breath and by the way
stuff's gonna mess up and trying to
change it into something good and then
he talks about that for like 10 days
you should be like wait guys like
we was talking about Donald and on
Sunday he switched it
he didn't switch it Peter
it is
right
okay uh gentleman is uh to take the
problems and turn them into a I don't
like to say opportunity I object to that
language there's lots of alarm
traditional language
interpretation of London that I object
to
I don't like it when you say turn a
problem into an opportunity because
opportunity means
unrealized potential
get it opportunity does not mean success
if you don't take an opportunity you
fail okay I don't like the language I
don't like it when people teach this
section and they say I'm returning a
problem into an opportunity but I'm like
what happens is the opportunity don't
work out
okay
I want to say turn the problem into
a wild success forget success too that's
so boring
wild exciting fun success okay all right
got it this next section because that's
the choice you're faced with when you
choose between yourself and other people
okay this should be the next part of
don't win
Eterna
a bad situation into wild success and if
you get good at this
you don't have a bad day there's no such
thing as a bad day even Terrible Things
yo your body's failing yeah cool I'll
work I'll use it for something
okay uh it's beautiful it's very
beautiful okay all right
he says Nick made tuned here
now in the days of screw-ups enigma
means
uh
in modern times when when stuff messes
up so frequently
there's a special Tibetan word for that
it's called Enigma okay Enigma means
when you make a tea
and you get to the bottom and there's
junk down at the bottom like little
leaves and stuff that's called nygma
it means that the junk
the last 10 percent the last junk 10
percent
is called nigma our whole world is last
junk 10 percent
times
uh looking back at the Glory Days of
Buddhism Buddhism is 99 dead in this
world
real Buddhism is 99 dead in this world
oh guess a lot of there's
some people are in Burma
all of China I suppose uh Sri Lanka
they're not okay
and
forget him it's a dead religion
99 it's a corpse okay it's gone
99 gone in this world it's almost gone
how many Buddhists in India
zero
there's zero
there's a small movement Among The
Untouchables
uh
precious to keep in this world
so he says look these are the Enigma
days which means it's a great times for
turning problems into
wild successes he says we're so lucky to
live in the garbage days
you know because there's more raw
material to turn into success okay he's
so funny he's like you're so lucky to
live at the end of Buddhism
uh because there's so much problems now
if you learn how to turn problems into
opportunities you're gonna be success
You're Gonna Be Wild success okay
means very lucky
to pick up
when you get problems in your Dharma
practice
you better learn how to flip them into
opportunities for wild success
they may not consent song and come to
Young
if you don't learn to turn problems into
opportunities for a wild success
uh you will lose your Dharma practice
sure means you will lose your Dharma
practice you won't be a Buddhist
if you don't know how to because of the
condition of the world right now
if you don't learn to turn problems into
wild success opportunities
you will fail in your Dharma practice
because of the situation
in the world right now there's a zero
Buddhism
because of the the situation in the
World At Large you better be able to
turn problems into
something better or or you're sure is a
terrible terrible expression
sure means to slip on the ice
sure means to fall down walking you know
down the stairs
sure sure means the Dharma slipped on
the ice
and the Dharma fell down the stairs and
that's the time these are those days
okay
so on the days that the Dharma fell down
the stairs
you better learn to
turn problems into something
some great Advantage okay cool
all right and well that's a teaser for
the tomorrow's tomorrow's class yeah
okay we got 15 minutes Uncle Tim for
q a of any type
so the first question guessler okay
comes from Gabriella Fuchs and she said
what are some obstacles
antidotes for being able to see yourself
as an enlightened being
and she says it's easier for me to
the others already as enlightened
helping me but to be able to see myself
that way seems more challenging
yeah good question
um
there's a weird thing uh
there's a thing in in Christianity and
and me and Veronica as I mentioned we're
enjoying watching a TV series called The
Chosen which is a beautiful beautiful
presentation of
and uh there's this
very serious uh
injunction this suggestion from Jesus
that says when you are generous
like you give five thousand dollars to
write synonym
Jesus says keep it secret don't tell
anybody Okay and like give do your
giving and
in secret you know like that's not my
style but uh
but there's this idea of doing it in
secret and and we grew up on that I grew
up on that
you know that's the teaching I was
brought up so
I think most of us
whichever part of the world we come from
we were pretty much told by our parents
that when you do good things don't
advertise it you know don't tell people
don't brag about it it kind of cheapens
the good thing
it makes it cheap or something
so
keep it quiet do good things don't tell
everybody
that's a very great it is a great
tradition
and then then the
abhidharma says uh no no she lum
what's it called
the four steps right
it's hard to
uh do the four steps
fourth step
of the fourth step the long name the
short name is Tonto tartuk means uh
celebrate
the good things you do celebrate them
the long
the long version of turtle is dakir tipa
dakir tipa means own it
make it your own
make it your own okay
and then we run around the world uh
teaching people in DCI there's almost
200 000 DCI students now
we teach them the four steps they live
on the four stems
the fourth step is
rejoicing tartuk or Dr Tampa own your
good deeds make them yours okay
and then um
didn't we go back a year later and we
talk to the same people and some people
are like yeah
you know I had this wild success you
know and some people say nothing
happened
and then we do the we do the cross check
it's called cross check
we checked the four steps did you do
number one yeah it did I have a goal in
mind did you do number two yeah I
identified someone to help did you do
number three yeah I helped them did you
do number four well
it's really frustrating for me because
it takes me like 10 minutes to get to
the well
you know and I'm like well you didn't do
number four did you which is what you
can call it coffee meditation but it
just means
when you go to sleep before you go to
sleep
never sleep with problems in your mind
never
okay it's really dumb
okay
the time for problems is The Breakfast
Table
when everything is glorious
you know
toast
with lots of peanut butter
that's breakfast it's hard to have a
problems are smaller in the light of day
when the sun comes up
problems get smaller okay it's really
dumb
to think about your problems when you're
going to bed okay that well gangster
what am I supposed to think about when I
go to bed
think about the good stuff you did today
okay I didn't do any good stuff today
you did but you're just not thinking
about it okay
why
partly what we've noticed in DCI
is the best people tend to have the most
trouble with coffee meditation
because they have this feeling that they
shouldn't brag about their Good Deeds
and that's a good thing that's a good
habit you know you shouldn't advertise
your good days to everybody except
yourself
accept yourself I'm sorry I'm eating in
the middle
same same the problems meditation for
the light of day
if you get up before dawn like I'm
forced to do
at Diamond Mountain
um
necessarily to get all the time zones
uh wait till the sun comes up
before you think about your problem okay
never
go to bed thinking about your problems
always fall asleep
thinking about the good things you did
today okay I didn't do any good things
today that's not true
that proves you haven't been sleeping
well
I practiced during the day Shin Tien
like
I'll I'll just practice falling off to
sleep with good thoughts like a couple
times a day
especially if someone's trying to tell
me something boring okay
um but
why am I talking about this because I
know the question didn't address that
but the question did address that
good people
tend to not acknowledge when they're
being good
okay good people
seem to have more trouble
and meaning they did something good
then bad people who didn't do anything
good who think they're doing good you
understand
so the people who have the most trouble
seeing themselves as a Buddha which is
the real question
uh it's Human Nature of good people
that they they don't somehow they don't
want to brag even to themselves
so you got to get over that
you gotta do coffee meditation you gotta
get in the habit
did we do good stuff today yes
what percent was it one
okay for everybody in this room I don't
care
except maybe uh
um okay we are not amazing people we are
not special people
but think about the good stuff you did
come on today when you fall asleep okay
and
you're we're not great practitioners and
we're not great Buddhists but um
we do do some good stuff
and if you focus on that
you'll it'll be easier for you to see
yourself as a Buddha okay
okay there's a famous
conversation
between a teacher and his student
this the teacher said
we got to go to the temple
why
it's sojung time
well what do you mean
we have to confess our mistakes for the
last two weeks you know
and the student said I don't need to
and the teacher said why
and if students said I'm badger yogini
I'm a perfect being
I don't have to purify myself
you know you just gave me initiation you
just spent weeks telling me how I'm a
perfect being
I don't need to go confess he said it
kicked him in the butt he said get to
the temple
he said budgie again is going to confess
today okay
okay I understand
[Music]
so that's
but the opposite's also true we're not
perfect
but we have the scene of perfectionist
in us we have Buddha nature all beings
have Buddha nature so if you can't
recognize that Buddha nature you are
cheating yourself and you are cheating
other people
you know it's not a noble thing
to deny your Buddha nature it's just a
mistake
it's it's a big mistake okay you are you
are a beautiful pure being
you just gotta polish them a little bit
okay but it's there it's all there okay
and if you don't then you failed as a
Buddha okay
at least you're not a Buddha I guess
I'm just kidding okay
uh
acknowledge your goodness especially
before you go to sleep that's the best
time of day to do it okay knowledge your
goodness don't be shy
to brag to yourself
that's a good habit and it makes you a
better better
person okay
all right Mr Tim
this is another question from online
sorry guys we got to give them some
opportunities online but we'll catch up
this is from Ola um
um I think this is interesting
she says if everything is coming from me
coming from my own seeds
when I die and pass on
well the people that I see now continue
to exist or not
foreign
and then I die then I don't know does
the universe stop and there's all the
people
I was projecting did they all stop so
the projecting is going on from two
sides right I mean they are projecting
themselves to themselves
and you are projecting them to yourself
so the only thing that ends is your
projection to yourself of them
but they still have their projection of
to themselves of them okay so no problem
they get to go on right
the interface is interesting
the interface between my projection of
you and your projection of you
is an interesting border to talk about
and um
we assume that
my projection of another person
if it doesn't exactly match
it's probably close to what they're
projecting you see what I mean we
believe that
I'm seeing Shin-chan in a certain way
in a certain way
I can't reach intense mind right now
but I can see a lot I know you for a
long time
and I we make an assumption
that that's what shinten is seeing also
but that's that's not logical
who knows what kind of seed she has
so the interaction Interfaith how how I
see her and how she sees her
God knows how she sees herself I don't
know I don't know what she's saying and
I will never know until I become a
Buddhism
I don't know what how you see how you
see yourself I just see how I see you
but in either case you are coming from
seeds okay in both cases you are coming
from
if you're a cease for something to
to end
if your seeds run out and sending ants
like your life
it doesn't prove anything about what
they're seeing they could be seeing
anything we don't know
way since we don't know
it's probably better to
my old boss at the diamond business he
was the Israeli you know the azerland
family
and uh
so I would I would donate most of my
income to to the monastery or to all for
19 years
and every six months we would
I would collect my salary
from the company and then donated they
would donate it directly
uh I didn't even get it it just was
donated directly I got a little bit to
buy bus tickets and stuff
and uh so uh
would there would be this negotiation
every six months you know and uh
these two tough Israeli investors you
know they would
we'd have a meeting
and I'd say well it's time for me to get
my money
and they'd say I'd say the CFO would
come in he'd say okay it's up to eighty
thousand ninety thousand seven hundred
and then uh
the CFO would say it's it's 89 300.
you know and I would
look at these
Israelis right I think let's make it an
even hundred you know and they're like
no
let's make it 120.
I'm like what
they said
no not me even hundred let's make it
let's make 150 what the hell you know
and I'd be like wow
I said can I ask you a personal question
and they said yeah
and I said you guys there's really
you're like all Jewish people then my
boss said the most Jewish I ever got was
throwing rocks at cars on Saturday
people driving their car inside I was
still rocks at them I said yeah but
you're not like Tibetan Brutus you know
why you
making these huge donations on top of my
salary why why are you doing that
and he looks to me in the eye and he
says you never know who's right
[Laughter]
and I'm like wow
that's so smart and he said yeah I cover
all I donate everything you know when I
get to heaven I can say yeah I donated
tonight
so you gotta have that attitude with
them with other people okay you don't
know who's Spooner
like don't
don't mess up
it's safer to assume everybody's a
burner and act that way
because some of them are
probably
and then you're covered
okay okay treat everybody like a Buddha
then you're not gonna offend any Buddha
right it's a lot more logical like my
Jewish boss okay
okay